A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Rights and Social Justice, Office Files of Lynn Walker Huntley FA692
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Rights and Social Justice, Office Files of Lynn Walker Huntley
1981-1997
Rockefeller Archive Center
Huntley, Lynn
Ford Foundation
FA692
14.65 Cubic Feet 8 Paige boxes, 5 LGL size Hollinger boxes, and 5 LTR size Hollinger boxes
Arrangement
Records are arranged into 4 series.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject Files, 1981-1997
Series 2. Consultant Files, 1983-1994
Series 3. Program Reviews and Meetings, 1987-1993
Series 4. Chronological Correspondence Files, 1986-1994
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Second group of Lynn Walker Huntely's office files was transferred to the RAC by the Ford Foundation in 2018 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2018:064. This accession was incorporated into the collection during processing in 2018.
Scope and Contents
Contains correspondence, consultant files, program reviews, meeting records and subject files.
Collection consists of more than one accession of Lynn Walker Huntley office files ingested by the RAC over the years. An accession processed in 2018 consisted of a group of subject files regarding the Ford Foundation's work with the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) and was added to the end of the Subject Files Series in order to reconstitute the relationship between the materials. Another box of Huntley office files was added from a different accession of unrelated Ford Foundation records (Accession 2018:063 of the Ford Foundation records, EMAC, MAC, Office Files of John P. Santos collection) later in 2018. It was determined during the processing of that accession that the materials were connected to the Huntley subject files that the RAC ingested in 2018, and thus the box was incorporated into Huntley's collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Other Finding Aids
Finding aids concerning the office files of other Ford Foundation officers in the Rights and Social Justice Program as well as the subsequent Human Rights and International Cooperation Unit of the Peace and Social Justice include:
FA594 Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Vice President, Office Files of Mary E. McClymont
FA674 Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Office Files of Mary E. McClymont
FA591 Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Human Rights and International Cooperation (HRIC), Office Files of Anthony D. Romero
FA597 Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Human Rights and International Cooperation (HRIC), Office Files of Mahnaz lspahani
FA590 Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Human Rights and International Cooperation (HRIC), Office Files of Alan Jenkins
FA613 Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Human Rights and International Cooperation (HRIC), Office Files of Cristina Eguizabal
Biographical / Historical
Lynn Walker Huntley (1945-2015) came to the Ford Foundation in 1982 to work as a Program Officer focusing on civil rights programs. She would eventually become Director of the Rights and Social Justice Program until she left the foundation in 1995. She served briefly as a consultant for Ford after leaving her position as Rights and Social Justice Director and was tasked with monitoring the foundation's grants to the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP).
Prior to her time at Ford, Huntley worked as a lawyer for the NAACP Legal Defense and Education Fund (LDF) in the 1970s. While with the LDF, she was part of the legal team that managed the Furman v. Georgia legal case. The U.S. Supreme Court's decision on the case in 1972 resulted in a temporary suspension of the death penalty within the whole nation. Huntley would later serve at the U.S. Department of Justice Civil Rights Division.
During her time at Ford, Huntley helped obtain funding for the U.S. Civil Rights Movement documentary Eyes on the Prize and started the African American Church Initiative. After leaving Ford, she joined the Southern Education Foundation, and in 2002, became president of that foundation.
Ford Foundation; Civil rights; African Americans -- Civil rights; Minorities--Civil rights; Women's rights
- Subject Files, 1981-1997; I
  Scope and Contents
  Series consists of the subject files Lynn Walker Huntley created to document her work in the Ford Foundation's Rights and Social Justice Program.
  It contains a significant number of files concerning the Foundation's support of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP). These records originate from a later accession of Huntley's office files that was processed in 2018. They mostly regard the financial, administrative, and legal troubles the NAACP experienced during the early and mid-1990s, the monitoring and disbursement of the Ford Foundation's funding to the organization and its Special Contribution Fund (SCF), the foundation's support for the NAACP's financial and strategic planning initiatives, the controversies surrounding the foundation's backing of the NAACP during this time period, some of the social justice and civil rights issues the NAACP focused on during the 1980s and 1990s, and questions concerning the NAACP's continued relevancy in advocating for racial equality and empowerment of racial minorities amidst its series of crises.
  Some of the subject files appear to have been created and maintained by Huntley's successor as Director of the Rights and Social Justice Program, Mary E. McClymont, as well as by other staff members of the Human Rights and International Cooperation Unit of the Peace and Social Justice Program which replaced the Rights and Social Justice Program during the foundation's reorganization in 1996. This may indicate that the offices for these programs continued to use and add to the subject files created during Huntley's term as Director of the Rights and Social Justice Program even after Huntley's departure from Ford.
  - ACLS Comparative Culturalism Project, 1985-1989 (Box 1)
  - Africa and the Middle East Program, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Africa Diaspora Research Project, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Asia File, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Civil Rights, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Committee to Improve Professional Opportunities for Minorities, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
  - League of Women Voters Education Fund, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Media Initiatives -- Working File, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
  - Media, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Media -- Working File, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Media, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - Minority Scholarships -- Correspondence, 1992 (Box 1)
  - NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund -- Working File, 1985-1992 (Box 1)
  - National Commission on Testing and Public Policy, 1989 January (Box 2)
  - Testing Materials, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Boston College Report Dissemination, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - National Commission on Testing and Public Policy -- Boston College Grant, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - Boston College, 1991 (Box 2)
  - National Commission on Testing and Public Policy -- Boston College Working File, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - National Commission on Testing and Public Policy -- California, University of, Working File, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Gifford, Bernard [CONFIDENTIAL], 1991 (Box 2)
  - Native American Task Force -- Working File, 1983-1985 (Box 2)
  - Ford Foundation Native American Consultancy, 1982 October (Box 2)
  - Trip Reports (Transferred to Unpublished Reports), undated (Box 2)
  - Adams, John Hurst -- Correspondence and Manuscript Re: Black Churches, 1993 (Box 8)
  - Africa Governance Meeting (November 13-15, 1990) -- Rapporteur Notes, 1990-1991 (Box 8)
  - Africa and the Middle East -- Ford Foundation Funding -- Democracy and Women's Programs, 1994 (Box 8)
  - Anderson, Bernard -- Consultancy -- Black Elected and Appointed Officials, 1993-1994 (Box 8)
  - Bicentennial of the U.S. Constitution -- Correspondence Re: Conferences, Reports, 1987 (Box 8)
  - Black Church -- Working File, 1993-1995 (Box 8)
  - Black Church (Endowed Congregations), 1994 (Box 8)
  - Black Churches -- Best Practices FAP, 1992-1993 (Box 8)
  - Black Church -- FAP Working File, 1991-1993 (Box 8)
  - Black Church -- Lilly Evaluation, 1994 (Box 8)
  - Black Church -- Review Materials, 1990-1991 (Box 8)
  - Community Development Activities, 1986 (Box 8)
  - Chicago Theological Seminary, 1986-1989 (Box 8)
  - Christian Methodist Episcopal Church -- Working File, 1988-1991 (Box 8)
  - Family Life Center, 1989-1992 (Box 8)
  - Ford Foundation Diversity Workshop (Trustees), 1994 (Box 8)
  - Franklin, Robert M. -- Correspondence and Memos Re: Black Churches, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Franklin, Robert -- Email, 1994-1995 (Box 8)
  - Howard University Divinity School -- Working File, 1986-1994 (Box 8)
  - Lincoln, C. Eric, 1990-1991 (Box 8)
  - Los Angeles Notes, 1993-1994 (Box 8)
  - Maryland, University of -- Andrew Billingsley and Black Church Study, 1988-1994 (Box 8)
  - Motivational Educational Entertainment (MEE) Report -- Re: At-Risk Urban Youth and Methods of Addressing Issues, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Pressley, Calvin, 1992-1993 (Box 9)
  - Rights and Social Justice -- Quarterly Projections, 1994 (Box 9)
  - Synopsis of Report on "Harassment of Black Elected Officials", 1983 August 8 (Box 9)
  - Turner Foundation -- Pregnancy, Child Care, and Family Initiatives, 1995 (Box 9)
  - Voter/Civic Participation, 1992-1996 (Box 9)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) reports, 1990-1992 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Special Contribution Fund (SCF), 1992-1995 (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Special Contribution Fund (SCF), 1990-1992 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Special Contribution Fund (SCF), 1983-1994 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Special Contribution Fund (SCF), 1983-1990 (Box 10, Folder 7-8)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Special Contribution Fund (SCF), 1985-1994 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Reserve Fund - Grant 930-0247, 1992-1995 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Special Contribution Fund (SCF) 500,000 dollars general support - Grant 680-0469, 1994-1995 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Special Contribution Fund (SCF) Recommended Grant Actions (RGAs), 1985-1992 (Box 11, Folder 12-14)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) key documents, 1992-1995 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) - Executive Summary of the Coopers and Lybrand Special Audit, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Articles regarding the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1994-1995 (Box 11, Folder 17-18)
  - Articles regarding the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), undated (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Articles regarding the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1994 June (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Ford Foundation memo and articles regarding the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1994-1996 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - National Association for the Advancement for Colored People (NAACP) Legal Defense and Education Fund (LDF) Civil Rights Institute, 1993-1995 (Box 12, Folder 22-23)
  - Craver, Matthews, Smith, and Company, 1995 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) grants monitor consultancy appointment, 1984-1995 (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Special Contribution Fund (SCF) Grant 680-0469, 1995-1996 (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Memos regarding the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1994-1996 (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Price Waterhouse 200,000 dollars - Grant 950-0321, 1994-1995 (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Price Waterhouse 500,000 dollars - Grant 950-0321, 1995-1996 (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Special Contribution Fund (SCF) Working file/Grant file, 1992-1994 (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Special Contribution Fund (SCF) Working file/Grant file - Annual Convention, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 31)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Special Contribution Fund (SCF) Working file/Grant file, 1992-1993 (Box 13, Folder 32-33)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Special Contribution Fund (SCF) Working file/Grant file Appendix A, 1992-1993 (Box 13, Folder 34)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Special Contribution Fund (SCF) Working file/Grant file Appendix B, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 35)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Special Contribution Fund (SCF) Working file/Grant file Appendix C, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 36)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Special Contribution Fund (SCF) Working file/Grant file, 1992-1994 (Box 13, Folder 37-38)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) correspondence - Part I, 1992-1994 (Box 13, Folder 39-41)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) correspondence - Part II, 1985-1996 (Box 14, Folder 42-44)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) correspondence - Part III, 1991-1994 (Box 14, Folder 45-47)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) correspondence, 1994-1996 (Box 14, Folder 48)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - Borges, Francisco, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 49)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - Evers-Williams, Myrlie, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 50)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - Financial report, 1990-1994 (Box 15, Folder 51)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - Internal memos, 1994-1995 (Box 15, Folder 52)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - Gibson, William, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 53)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - Jonas, Gil, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 54)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - Koprowski, John, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 55)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - NAACP Staff Meeting, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 56)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - National Board of Directors, 1994-1995 (Box 15, Folder 57)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - Press materials/Lloyd Garrison, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 58)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - Price Waterhouse, 1994-1995 (Box 15, Folder 59)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - Release of grant funds letter, 1994 October 7 (Box 15, Folder 60)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - Recent Recommended Grants Actions (RGAs), 1990-1994 (Box 15, Folder 61-62)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file, 1994-1995 (Box 15, Folder 63)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - Shinhoster, Earl, 1994-1995 (Box 15, Folder 64)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - Springs, Lennie, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 65)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - Watson, Denton report, 1992-1994 (Box 15, Folder 66)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - Wilmer, Cutler, and Pickering, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 67)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Working file - Lawsuits relating to the NAACP, 1994-1995 (Box 15, Folder 68)
  - Mhanaz Ispahani collected Recommended Grant Actions (RGAs), 1987-1997 (Box 16, Folder 69-71)
  - Craver, Mathews, Smith, and Company weekly reports, 1994-1995 (Box 16, Folder 72)
  - Council on Foundations and other organizations, 1992-1995 (Box 16, Folder 73-74)
    Original folder was unlabeled. File contains documents related to the Council on Foundations, the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), and the First Nations Development Institute.
  - Correspondence, 1984-1996 (Box 17, Folder 75-78)
    Chief correspondents of the Ford Foundation Rights and Social Justice Program (and later Peace and Social Justice Program) within the file include Lynn Walker Huntley, Anthony Romero, and Mary McClymont.
    The correspondence regards public housing and housing desegregation, domestic violence, minority rights, women's rights, African American churches, the care and maintenance of the Reverend Jesse Jackson papers, and the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP).
  - Legal - Women's rights reserve request, 1997 (Box 17, Folder 79)
    File regards a reserve request for a capacity building initiative involving flagship civil rights and women's rights organizations.
  - Legal - Women's rights reserve request, 1996-1997 (Box 17, Folder 80-81)
  - Miscellaneous - Johns Hopkins University, 1997 (Box 17, Folder 82)
  - Miscellaneous - Overseas Development Council (ODC), 1997 (Box 17, Folder 83)
  - Miscellaneous - New Priorities Abroad and New Voices at Home, 1991-1997 (Box 17, Folder 84-85)
  - Miscellaneous - Past RGAs, 1988-1996 (Box 18, Folder 86)
  - Foundation for the National Capital Region - Presidential Internship Fund, 1994-1995 (Box 18, Folder 87-89)
- Consultant Files, 1983-1994; II
  - Anderson, Bernard -- Consultancy, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
  - Cose, Ellis -- Consultancy, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
  - Jones, Charles H., Jr. -- Consultant -- Working File, 1983-1991 (Box 2)
  - Twyner, III, Olger C., 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Valdez, Armando -- Consultant, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Weaver, Robert, 1986 (Box 2)
- Program Reviews and Meetings, 1987-1993; III
  - Human Rights and Governance Meeting, London, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Rights and Social Justice Program Review Materials -- Papers, Background Materials, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Rights and Social Justice Meeting, Capetown, South Africa, 1993 May (Box 3)
  - Rights and Social Justice -- Program Review Meeting -- Program Review, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Rights and Social Justice -- Program Review Meeting -- Urban Poverty Worldwide Meeting, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Rights and Social Justice -- Program Review, 1993 December (Box 3)
- Chronological Correspondence Files, 1986-1994; IV
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1987 March-June (Box 3)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1987 July-December (Box 3)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1986 October-1987 February (Box 3)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1988 January-May (Box 4)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1988 June-December (Box 4)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1989 January-May (Box 4)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1989 June-September (Box 4)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1989 October-1990 February (Box 4)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1990 March-June (Box 5)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1990 July-October (Box 5)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1990 November-1991 February (Box 5)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1991 March-May (Box 5)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1991 June-September (Box 5)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1991 October-1992 January (Box 6)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1992 February-June (Box 6)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1992 June-July (Box 6)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1992 August-September (Box 6)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1992 October-December (Box 6)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1993 January-March (Box 7)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1993 March-April (Box 7)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1993 May-July (Box 7)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1993 August-October (Box 7)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1993 November-December (Box 7)
  - Lynn Walker-Huntley Correspondence, 1994 January-March (Box 7)